<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Portfolio on Novel Systems Engineering</title><link>https://novelsystems.me/portfolio/</link><description>Recent content in Portfolio on Novel Systems Engineering</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://novelsystems.me/portfolio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>DDR Sensor — Material-Discriminating LiDAR for Maritime SAR and Radar Augmentation</title><link>https://novelsystems.me/portfolio/maritime-ddr-lidar-sensor/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://novelsystems.me/portfolio/maritime-ddr-lidar-sensor/</guid><description>Invented a polarization-based LiDAR architecture that classifies objects by material composition — distinguishing survival equipment and persons in water from ocean background, or carbon-fiber drones from birds — by exploiting water and atmosphere as near-zero depolarization backgrounds. A dual orthogonal 1D silicon photonic phased array achieves 128x phase shifter reduction, transforming physical defect yield from 74% to 98.5% and bringing sensor costs from $50,000–200,000 down to $600–800. Two provisional patents filed covering the core DDR architecture, adaptive environmental calibration, shared-aperture autonomous target acquisition, and distributed perimeter sensor networks; SBIR Phase I submitted to U.S. Coast Guard.</description></item><item><title>The Birthmark Standard — Hardware-Backed Photo Authentication</title><link>https://novelsystems.me/portfolio/birthmark-standard-photo-authentication/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://novelsystems.me/portfolio/birthmark-standard-photo-authentication/</guid><description>Founded a 501(c)(3) nonprofit and designed the complete technical architecture for a privacy-preserving photo authentication system — from camera sensor fingerprinting through blockchain registration — establishing the Birthmark Media Registry as background infrastructure for validating whether images seen online actually originated from a camera.</description></item></channel></rss>